JESUS MANUEL ORTIZ

jesusmoh89@gmail.com | (786) 630 5797 | LinkedIn | Miami, FL 33134 | Visit my site

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with over a decade of experience in the IT field, specializing in Java Full Cycle development for more than seven years and expertise in Fintech, Retail, and IT Healthcare industries, where I have made significant contributions in roles such as Senior Java Developer with cloud expertise and Java Full-Stack Developer for Angular/Android. (I'm more than just a coder, I'm a problem solver).

HARD SKILLS

Java | Spring Cloud | JUnit | test-container | JMeter | JSP | SOLID | Git | Maven | Jira | Android | AWS | API design | SDKs | Cloud | ELK | Microservices | Ngnix | JS | EC2 | Angular | DevOps | Confluence | Database Design | SQL | NoSQL | MVC | JakartaEE | S3 | Kubernetes | Docker | Linux | Docker-Compose | Hyper-V | RAID | ETL | VSCode | PCI | Serverless | TypeScript | J2EE.

SOFT SKILLS

Team Player | Multitasking | Self-Taught Learner | Spanish Speaker | Effective Leadership in Small Teams | Tolerance

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

FISERV (Global Fintech) | Senior Software Development Engineer (II) | Team size 5 | May 2021 – Dec 2023 | U.S.A

- **Developed Spring/Angular** solutions for payment processing, such as gateway-payments/switches and offered **top-tier assistance** for financial switching (transactions) among POS terminals, ATM, e-commerce, and financial authorizers with specifications REST, ISO8583, and SOAP.
- Optimized backup time for logs by 60%, bolstering data security and reducing potential system downtime.
- Implemented integration tests with Selenium, Junit, and Docker, resulting in a 40% decrease in production issues.
- In 2022, I contributed to Fiserv Uruguay's success in becoming the first payment network, capturing over 50% of the Uruguayan payments market across all ecosystems.
- As part of the **FSwitchUY team**, we prioritized maintaining robust solutions through continuous updates and timely resolution of *critical security issues*. This, combined with other key objectives, enabled the company's sustained growth.

SISNET (Software Provider for Retail/Logistic) | Senior Software Development Engineer | Team size 6 | Nov 2017 – May 2021 | URU

- Implemented Java backend solutions (Rest/SOAP APIs) using Jakarta, Payara Micro, Cache and Hibernate resulting in a 40% improvement in API response time, and enhanced system POS terminal performance.
- Design a roadmap to upgrade and transform legacy monolithic to microlites and microservices.
- Achieved a UI/UX for the Android mobile App and admin panel resulting satisfaction and positive feedback.

SASA (Retail auto-parts) | IT technical leader & Senior Software Development Engineer | Team size 6 | Sep 2014 – Nov 2017 | CUB

- Configured and planned strategic infrastructure upgrades for 14 on-premises dependencies, delivering a highly available solution that leveraged Hyper-V, Active Directory, RAID, and HP ProLiant servers, achieving a 99.00% increase in system uptime.
- Developed a Java-based solution from the ground up to categorize slow-moving inventory at the company, resulting in a cost reduction of \$500,000 by applying the Pareto principle.
- Achieved a 70% decrease in processing time for ETL tasks related to stock status processing using Pentaho and Scala to support parallel processing of large datasets.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering, Technological University of Havana (CUJAE), Cuba, September 2009 – July 2014

CERTIFICATIONS AND BADGES

<u>AWS Certified Developer Associate</u> | <u>AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate</u> | <u>AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner</u> | <u>ACG Kubernetes & Terraform</u> | <u>AWS DynamoDB Deep Dive.</u>

RESEARCH PROJECTS AND INITIATIVES

PHP | WooCommerce | Wix | Node.js | AI/ML | HL7 | HCE | PCI | GraalVM | Kotlin | Shopizer | GCP | Pentaho | Scala